Discerning a mind of ill will or lust is
beneficial for not acting out of those
intentions. Why is it beneficial
Why is it beneficial
to discern a neutral mind?
Um well, because the the neutral
uh neutral mind, how you call it, or
neutral feeling,
uh
because if that's not discerned,
uh a person is kind of uh
um automatically
abiding in a certain, say, activated
state. Let's say that way. So, if you're
not discerning a a neutrality of your
mind, you're looking past it, and then
looking past always implies some
involvement, some pressure, some
direction, which means you're going to
land on either lust or aversion,
depending which way it takes you, so to
speak. So, one needs to be withdrawn from lust,
So, one needs to be withdrawn from lust,
withdrawn from aversion,
but neutrality needs to be discerned cuz
it's not recognized as peaceful.
It's not recognized as the right
balance. So, that's why discerning the neutral
So, that's why discerning the neutral
feeling is what will establish the mind
in samadhi,
even even more so than through
um
being imperturbable in regard to lust
and aversion, which is also, as I said,
a necessary step.
But the neutrality in and of itself,
when seen, when understood, it's
pleasant and peaceful and recognized as
such, which means then the mind will have even
which means then the mind will have even
less of an incentive to to turn back to
desire or ill will or or other forms of
uh engagement with the world and
activations and so on.
So, I can discern that there is neutral
I can discern that there is neutral
feeling, and practically Mhm.
what extra steps do I need to take to become
extra steps do I need to take to become
more stable?
>> Yeah, you should like
Yeah, everybody would have, say, a um
some recognition of
neutral feeling, neither pleasant nor
unpleasant. It's neither good nor bad.
Uh but as I said, the the tendency of a
mind that's still not trained, not free
from craving completely, is to
well, to have some resistance towards
that neutrality.
So, like whenever a person whenever you
find yourself in a situation that's, you
know, neither disturbing, not not really
unpleasant, not terribly pleasant
either, kind of just even,
uh you need to actively make the effort
to to uh
discern, to contemplate uh the
peacefulness of it, the value of it.
Because the mind will not see it
magically on its own.
It's not going to be like a grand reveal
of look at this peace. You got to work
through that, as I said, um
subtle kind of resistance that the mind
has towards neutrality, and actually
teach it that no, no, no, this is
peaceful. This is the balance.
Protect this.
Cuz it's not going to be obvious in and
of itself, because as I said, peace,
it's often for people uh becomes
boredom. It becomes something you just uh
It becomes something you just uh
Right, okay, fine, but uh what's next?
What's the next involvement? What's the
next activation? Where's the next uh
engagement? Cuz that's what keeps the
mind um um
well,
kind of content in a way. People are
contented by being engaged and driven,
because otherwise uh
feeling neutral, feeling bored, it it
becomes it it it becomes like too heavy.
It becomes something like you don't want
to feel because again, there's there's
no recognition of the value of that.
So, contemplate the peaceful aspect of
the neutral feeling.
And when you notice the mind kind of
resisting, wanting to move on to the
next thing, it's like, well, no, why?
Hold on. What's the rush? What's the
rush? I mean, I spent my whole life
moving from one thing to the other.
I can spend another hour not moving onto
the next thing and just stay with this
neutral feeling, even if the mind starts
to resist it and so on.
So, would that increase the contrast
between the neutral feeling and
pleasant feeling and
painful feeling?
Uh um
I'm not sure if I would put it that way.
I think it would more like increase um
mind's familiarity.
So, because the more you overlook the
feeling, the more driven you are by it,
naturally. So, just a a very ignorant,
uninstructed person that has no concept
of recollecting, you know, what's
currently felt or practicing restraint
or saying no to the initial impulse,
uh the reason why they're so driven is
cuz they're perpetually looking way past
what's being felt as the uh uh immediate
um
direct kind of pressure, which is the
reason for motivation and for the action
and so on.
So, the more you're becoming familiar
with it, the more space is created
between you and that impulse to act out,
so to speak.
In other words, it will be less and less
urgent for you to Yeah, I must address this
for you to Yeah, I must address this
feeling. I must get rid of the
unpleasure displeasure. I must pursue
the pleasure. I I you know, I can't help
but but acting out of like
uh the it will take longer for that uh
uh momentum of craving
to to get to its force, to its full
force, which means you have more time to
say no to it and uh
uh subdue it and not act out of it.